welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
check-ins my wife made me a grilled
cheese sandwich just sitting right in
front of me
um and i'm smelling it and uh all the
things are coming alive there uh
a little bit hungry and uh super
excited for this session welcome to the
stoa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and the stowe is a place for us to
go here and dialogue about what matters
most at the knife's edge of this moment
and today we have my buddy nick benjamin
um and nick uh he came to me this guy's
awesome by the way like like
first on top of the storm like who the
is this guy i gotta be his friend
and then we started becoming friends by
you know zooming in each other and
hanging out
and got to know his uh world view a
little bit more and some ideas
and i invited him to uh
come to the space and do whatever he
wants really and he suggested this
really
interesting psychotechnology sort of a
psycho technology for those who don't
know the term sort of like a
transformational
practice that can change the way you
look at the world
and operate in it and he mentioned he
was
working on something for a while called
concept unfolding
and it's the idea of
you know what i'll let him explain it
but it's juicy
so that being said 60 minutes is an
interactive session and i'll hand it
over to nick
hi everybody um i'm happy to be here
thank you so much peter for the
introduction
so a little bit about me um a former
engineer and rabel rouser
turned entrepreneur with a taste in
literature
in philosophy poetry classical piano and
overly complex scrabble words
i'm also the co-founder of the brain a
web platform for organizing humanities
knowledge
we create visual knowledge graphs to
help people conduct better sense making
in choice making a lot of my work
centers around
ontological questions so questions about
what is what is a concept what are ideas
how do you map them
how do you make them and this is where
this presentation comes in so i'm going
to share my screen
bear with me um super experimental
psychotech
never done this before in person
tell me if you guys you guys see my
screen
okay cool so concept unfolding
is the alchemical art of concept
creation while chemical
we'll get to that but first the limits
of my language are the limits
of my world ludwig withgenstein said
this and i believe it
um my question to you is can we
consciously expand
the limits of our language to midwife a
more beautiful world
right so
don't want to lose my voice this early
into the presentation i don't know why
that's happening
um so concept unfolding is is the
systematic generation of new ideas
from incipient concepts so in this
session i want to familiarize you with
this psychotech
by demonstrating in action um initiating
breakout sessions so that you guys can
use it
allow your creative juices to flow and
hopefully help emerge a set of
completely new concepts
so how does it work
building blocks are concepts which are
morphemes like
horse which are the the the unit words
in compound words like horsemanship for
example
uh so so a lot of the concepts that we
use democracy
have dem have two words within
themselves or several morphemes within
them
demos kratos people power power of the
people
for example uh and along with concepts
lenses or functions or morphisms so
people familiar
with uh the mathematical uh
subdiscipline of category theory
will understand what a morphism is it's
just like a mapping from one concept to
another or a function
we're gonna see it's a lot simpler than
what it sounds like um
the process is choose a concept choose a
lens
run the concept through the lens define
the resulting concept
and then assess its usefulness and
that's kind of what it looks like you
got your original
pentagon you run it through a lens then
you get a diamond
right but to make this really juicy i'm
going to
stop sharing my screen and perhaps you
guys can see this
or i spent like part of the day doing
origami i'm really bad at it
so this is a swan in the swan
peter can you see this okay cool
so so the swan could unfold
in the in concept space right into a
pyramid just use your imagination here
or a dragon this drag it's so hard to
make dragons
um but i i did my best we want we wanted
to
we want swans to unfold into dragons or
dragons into swans we don't want these
kind of like nothing concepts
and and i'm gonna i'm gonna give you a
disclaimer as to why
concept unfolding is a terrible psycho
technology before i proceed any further
and just like shoot myself in the foot
so back to sharing my screen
right so why is this a terrible
psychotec
a high degree of freedom so essentially
when you have concepts that are
recombinable with concepts
you have um infinite combinatorial
an infinite combinatorial system so
and then we can recombine the concepts
that have been combined with other
concepts and so this system grows
infinitely and expands into itself
exponentially which means it's
computationally intractable
what does that mean you can't complete
you don't have time to completely
explore the space
um and uh and so it's not it's not
possible
to navigate this exhaustively the space
cannot know itself
another another term for this a physics
term is non-ergodicity
you can't possibly exhaustively explore
the space
um so so essentially our we can use our
our creativity to its maximum capacity
but we're going to be lost in this
expect exponentially large space
of course before the cart problem as
you'll see
concepts are used to label experiences
in conscious awareness
um and so but right now what we're doing
is creating concepts
absent the reference so absent the thing
to which the concept
points to we're just engaging in the
abstract creation of concepts
that's an exceptionally hard thing to do
um very disorienting no concept compass
so we don't know which direction to go
in concept space that is maximally
relevant so if i take this
i can't see it again i have to un unsure
it's a really clumsy presentation guys
so if i take this concept space
right here um it's not flat there are
peaks and valleys
right um peaks represent
local optima so places where concepts
are are pretty useful
and there may be global optima somewhere
we can un possibly unfold language
in a direction that is maximally optimal
meaning
it will contribute maximally to human
flourishing
right because the limits of my language
are the limits of my world
but we don't know where that direction
is so
i have some open questions that i'll
share with you before i um
before i break you out into rooms i'm
just gonna move my origami back
and share the screen again
all right so let's get to the juicy
stuff
zapper wharf hypothesis so sapir and
wharf were two
linguists who hypothesize that the
structure of language
affects your worldview now there are two
versions of this hypothesis the strong
version
which is that the structure of your
language determines your cognition
in the weak version which is that the
structure of language influences your
cognition
regardless of which one you you ascribe
to
language and the way in which you
experience
the world are related and the richer
your language
the more nuanced your world view um and
and so on so the more fine grained it is
now imagine a world without the words
love beauty truth
good freedom bittersweetness wonder what
would that world be like
without the way in which to label those
experiences would we have those
experiences at all
that's what the sapr war hypothesis is
getting to
milton in paradise law said to name is
to create
so knowing the names of things we
increase our affordances in the world to
use it for vacant term
we notice them our experiences become
more nuanced
more fine-grained so who do we ought to
thank for these
limitless cultural gifts that we've
inherited in language
so many worms words were coined by poets
and philosophers scientists and other
thinkers to free language
as an example milton created
approximately 630 words
shakespeare it's it depends on who you
ask but
between 200 and 500 and if you take
whole
expressions up to a thousand five
hundred
and that's that's huge considering the
common
american only uses up to 3 000 words
um and uh i think that the common common
british english uses up to eight
thousand and in shakespeare's time
he is working vocabulary it was 25.
james joyce's was 38
000 that's insane take a sip of water
so the um illustrious forebears of word
coinagery you can see here that i
coined a word um pythagoras
is attributed with the word philosophy
and monad sappho with blue kupikran
which means sweet bitter we use it as
bittersweet that feeling of
love was amazing but now it's terrible
because she broke up with me i'm
familiar with that
um chaucer obscure superstitious
contract hobbs rift on chaucer with
social contract
shakespeare's got tons i mean what would
a world world be like without the word
bump right accused invulnerable gloomy
and so on right
so where do these concepts arise from
where are they located this is a
metaphysical
question that's been asked throughout
the ages you'll find it within
um the annals of philosophy for for you
metaphysicians out there we're going to
just run rough
rough shot over your ontological claims
and
structures so please bear with me
another disclaimer um
the the aleph is a term that was uh used
by jorge luis borges
in his short stories denoting a hick
stance and a hick stance is a single
point that's outside of space
from where all space can be first
perceived so it's a point in space that
contains all other points in space
um so we can envision the world of idea
this this
space of all possible concepts as a high
stance
as a as a space outside of space and
time that contains all possible concepts
and this this type of trope has been
used throughout the ages
cora in in plato's uh timaeus the
amorphous space of all probable
distributions used by
actually discovered this recently uh
it's basically the language
lattice this is used by paul a hungarian
german
french poet the imaginal realm for those
of you familiar with verbacy
he explores a lot of bounds work
so it's a place in our imagination where
things take on integrity or existence
donors who believes that philosophy is
the art of concept creation
calls this space where where concepts
are created
and maintained the plane of imminence
and there's several
others i like to use the adjacent
possible so this is where i can take my
swan and unfold it into many things that
are
that have the swan seed inside of them
but that are not swans they may be
dragons i don't know
moving on what are lenses so a lens is a
function that takes your concept and
turns it into another concept
i've created a bunch again super
experimental
um this will make a lot of sense when i
show you the
sheet that i should have shared with you
by now which i'll send to you shortly
um essentially we will take a we'll take
a concept for example
uh universe and then we'll run it we'll
turn this
thing into a process right into a verb
so for example we'll add an ing and put
it in its gerund form it's present
participle so what is universing
then we we provide a definition for that
what is
nash equilibrating that's taking the
words nash equilibrium
and adding ing to them and turning it
into a process right
this is a process philosophy move you
see this a lot
in heidegger heidegger takes the term
world and turns it into worlding
world the world worlds itself okay
we can take prefixes and then snap them
on to words
uh or suffixes as well so that's
this obviously requires a basic
understanding of latin and greek
but i mean you can you can figure it out
given your knowledge of english words
so what's what is proto-sovereignty i'm
just playing around with these concepts
here no more fold what's a normal fold
it's a way of folding the law right um
a demon word right turning towards the
demon
just making up words here metaphilia uh
something that we see often in the game
b
slash stoa space who was just in love
with going meta and everything
um knife sedgness right what is that
what is that peculiar quality of
of stoa experience that has has a
knife's edge
you know attribute to itself um
word fusion taking two words and just
smashing them together uh so a generally
an adjective and a noun but you can have
two nouns for example a noun phrase
libidino capitalisms that that constant
desire to consume
um that that fuels this
the world that we live in uh flaming
metagame i don't know what that is
but bear with me um basic metaphor so
it's a
rhetorical lens x is why consciousness
is a blooming lotus so it's a form of
equivalence
that shares the attributes of one
concept with another
an anti-static one this is really
interesting this is just taking
uh a prefix or a suffix um and
substituting it in or out
um rather taking a syllable and
substituting it with another syllable
within the term so taking feedback
removing feed and then adding fold which
creates fold back
um and removing back and then adding
fourth and then defining those
i've had fun playing with feedback
fullback and fold forth in
a discussion on letter with a friend um
finally x gaining the attributes of y
kind of like
metaphorical um i call these the phase
and mythical lenses but you guys can
create your own lenses here what is
liquid truth
what is solid sunshine does it matter
maybe
um what is the story of all thefts can
we envision
a story that that incorporates every
single theft that ever occurred
would that be useful as a that's a
storytelling move or
wonder as a misguided creator god so
apotheosizing the word wonder into a god
and then having a dialogue with it
as a misguided god i don't know what
that is but
poets have done this for ages and it's
fun
all right moving forward like i said
basic basic example universe turn it
into a verb
versing and i define that or proffer or
a tentative definition
the singing that brings all there is
into being or the memetic act of
losing the ego and becoming all there is
you could call that non-dualism but this
is just offers
another another flexible entry into
language or into
into experience actually and widens
widens your world
does it sound crazy yup and that's
because it is
i've already offered all of the
disclaimers um
the reasons why it's terrible there's
way too many there's way too much
freedom in it
it's it's tough to find constraints to
make this a useful psychotec but this is
why i want to
try and experiment with you guys so a
couple of open questions that i have is
is it possible to to conduct systematic
concept unfolding
that generates useful concepts so in
order for that to be possible is there a
deep code is there some kind of pattern
within language that permits the
exploration of
concept space through the judicious
combination of lenses and concepts to
move in the direction of greatest
flourishing of humankind right can we
can we do that
um is it possible to discover those
category-specific
directions of unfolding optimal
directions of unfolding
and what are the constraining criteria
that we can set in order to make sure
that we
we achieve relevance realization so that
we find things that are relevant
as outputs of concept lens combinations
okay
lots of words now now comes the fun part
um i'm gonna stop sharing
and uh i will share with you
two things an orientation document
which provides you with the with that
table of lenses if you want to use your
own lens
if you want to use the lenses that i
provide or you can create your own
lenses
and what we're going to do is hop onto a
google sheet together
and uh you'll be in a breakout room with
someone else
you'll talk about what feels most alive
for you that's probably the best way
into
coming up with the concept that actually
matters
and then you'll run that you'll choose a
lens you'll run that concept through a
lens
take the output and define it and then
write that into the google sheet
at the end we'll come back out we'll all
vote just like
put a a score on 10 on on the the
different rows
um that for concepts that appeal to you
and then for the ones that have the
highest score we're going to discuss
those
and if we have more time we'll do
another breakout session so
share
there we go
okay that's the google
doc and here's the google sheet
so peter um feel free to break everybody
out into
into uh how many per rooms
um two two okay let's do it
[Music]
okay there we go great so we'll have um
10 minutes to engage in that kind of
concept unfolding cool all right
did you guys accept your rooms or okay
there we go
stop recording